"Lesser Known NAD+ boosting Supplements - Tryptophan, NADH, NMNH, and NRH"
Taking niacin,
also called nicotinic acid,
would be about 50 times
more efficient
than taking
the amino acid tryptophan
to boost NAD+,
because only about two percent
of tryptophan
is converted into niacin.
Also, tryptophan didn't work
to improve mitochondrial
or muscle function
in physically compromised
older adults,
even when combined
with niacin or nicotinamide.
And side effects
of taking tryptophan
include belching and gas,
blurred vision,
diarrhea, dizziness,
drowsiness, dry mouth,
headache, heartburn,
and potentially
a life-threatening condition
known as eosinophilia-myalgia
syndrome, or EMS.
There was an epidemic of EMS
tied to tryptophan supplements
from a single supplier
back in 1989
that led to their removal
from the market
for about 15 years.
Some sort of contaminant
was suspected,
but the cause
remains a mystery.
To this day,
tryptophan supplements
continue to be tainted
with impurities,
with at least one case
of EMS reported
decades after
the initial epidemic.
A case of EMS tied to
a bizarre weight loss diet
involving hundreds of cups
(~48 L) of cashews,
a rich source of tryptophan,
suggests the syndrome
can be caused
by excess tryptophan directly.
If anything,
tryptophan restriction
may be beneficial.
Nearly 50 years ago,
it was demonstrated
that restricting
dietary tryptophan
reduced cancer rates
and increased
the lifespans of rats
and, subsequently, mice.
Vegetarians and vegans
both appear to have
significantly lower intakes
of tryptophan,
but only in vegans
does this translate
to lower
tryptophan blood levels,
though presumably not
if they were to take
tryptophan supplements.
What about taking NAD+ directly?
This isn't practical
because of instability
and poor bioavailability.
NAD+ is vulnerable to heat,
pH, light, and oxygen,
requiring dark desiccant storage
at ideally 20 degrees (-29°C)
below freezing.
NAD+ can be given intravenously,
a practice started
in the 1950s
as an "underground" treatment
for alcoholism,
but when taken orally,
NAD may be broken down
in the alkaline environment
of the small intestine,
and NADH,
the so-called "reduced" form
of NAD+,
is broken down
in the acidic conditions
of the stomach.
(In organic chemistry,
the gain of a hydrogen atom
is said to quote-unquote
"reduce" the molecule,
so NADH
is the reduced form of NAD+).
Enteric forms of NAD+
could potentially survive
the digestive tract, but,
with the exception of neurons,
NAD can't cross
into mammalian cells.
This is why
NAD+ precursor supplements,
like NMN and NR,
were developed.
Also, there are evidently
(unpublished) data
showing that straight NAD+
can cause severe hyperglycemia
in mice.
Has it been tested in people?
NAD+ boosting supplements
have been found
to improve the learning
and memory of rodent models
of Alzheimer's disease
in the lab.
In 1995, case reports
of apparent benefit of NADH
for Alzheimer's disease
were published.
By the next year, an open-label
pilot study was published,
suggesting it had
a protective effect,
but without
a placebo control group,
the only conclusion
that could be drawn
was to study it further,
especially since
a similar study
with the same dose
over approximately
the same period
found no evidence
of any cognitive effects.
There have been
two randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials
of NAD precursors
for Alzheimer's.
One found no benefit
for memory, attention,
or clinician ratings
of dementia severity,
but did maybe find
less of a drop
in one dementia rating scale
after six months
of 10 milligrams a day of NADH.
The other, a six-month study
of nicotinamide,
failed to find
any clinical effects.
What about trying
NMNH and NRH,
the reduced forms
of NMN and NR?
They both appear
to boost NAD+ higher
than their
non-reduced counterparts.
In vitro,
NMNH can raise NAD+ levels
up to 10 times higher than NMN,
and NRH (also known as
dihydronicotinamide riboside)
is up to about 50 times
more potent than NR.
There are concerns
about stability of NRH
outside the body,
since it's sensitive to oxygen
and moisture,
but within the body,
NRH may be more stable,
not rapidly devolving
into nicotinamide,
like NR does
(at least in mouse blood).
However, unlike NR,
NRH does not appear
to be able
to significantly increase levels
in mouse muscles.
NRH is said to have
a "spectacular potency"
for increasing NAD+ levels,
perhaps the most potent
precursor discovered to date.
This may not necessarily be
a good thing.
The extreme boost
afforded by NRH
had detrimental consequences
in human liver cells in vitro,
resulting from
an excessive accumulation
of free radicals.
In addition to oxidation,
NRH was also found
promote inflammation.
Pro-inflammatory effects
were noted for NRH
on human immune cells in vitro
(but not for NMN, NAM, or NR).
Because it appears that NMNH
is converted to NRH
to enter cells,
these potentially
deleterious effects
may be shared
by NMNH as well
(though this has yet
to be tested).